Finding Aid for Summit Medical Center Records, 1969-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Summit Medical Center records 1969-2003 1970-1985
Summit Medical Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
0.7 linear feet
88298 Bf 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan based non-profit charitable corporation established to provide low-cost health services to low-income individuals and families. The records document the administration and to a lesser degree, the activities of the Summit Medical Center corporation and its clinics. Photographs include portraits of founder, Edward Pierce, and other staff physicians; and photographs of building, staff, and patients.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were donated by Mr. Lloyd T. Williams (Donor No. 7557 ) on May 25, 1988, and by Marcia Barrabee (Donor No. 5820 ) on August 23, 2004.
The record group is open to research.
The Summit Medical Center was incorporated by Albert Coudron, Lloyd Williams, Peter Darrow, and Melvin Pierce on August 23, 1968, at the behest of Pierce's son, Edward Pierce, M.D.
Edward Pierce received his M.D. at the University of Michigan in 1959. He joined a private practice in Ann Arbor, and was elected to the Ann Arbor city council, representing the Fourth Ward in 1964. Dr. Pierce left his practice and founded the Summit Medical Center (SMC) after unsuccessfully running for mayor of Ann Arbor in 1967. SMC opened a clinic in a small house at 403 Summit Street on September 1, 1968.
Jerry Walden, another graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School, joined Dr. Pierce at the Summit Street clinic on July 1, 1969. In 1971, they moved the clinic to an historic house at 704 Spring Street, where the Model Neighborhood Health Corporation rented the second floor for a dental clinic until 1981.
In 1973, the city of Ann Arbor approached SMC and asked them to expand their operations into another area of the city. With revenue sharing funds from the city of Ann Arbor, and private contributions, SMC established the Packard Community Clinic at 3174 Packard Road in September of 1973. Dr. Walden lead the staff at the new clinic. SMC acquired the Packard clinic building in 1977, and at the urging of Dr. Walden, a new corporation was spun-off by SMC on September 1, 1979, to oversee operations of the Packard Community Clinic. The Packard clinic building was expanded that same year.
Dr. Pierce retired from SMC in 1976 to pursue a career in politics. He returned to Ann Arbor in 1982, and once again went into private practice. Perpetually struggling financially, SMC was forced to close the Spring Street clinic in 1985. The corporation was dissolved, and its assets, including the house at 704 Spring Street, and liabilities were transferred to Child and Family Services of Washtenaw County.
The records of the Summit Medical Center are arranged alphabetically by topic. The records contain information pertaining to years as early as 1969, and as late as 2003. The bulk of the records were produced between 1970 and 1985, inclusive. The records document the administration and to a lesser degree, the activities of the Summit Medical Center corporation and its clinics. The administration of the Packard Community Clinic as an independent corporation (from 1979-2003) is also documented in a separate file titled Packard Community Clinic. Some of the records also document the relationships between SMC and the major insurance companies, the Johnson Foundation, the Model Cities Program, the Washtenaw County Word of God Community, and John Williams, DDS. Records in the group were produced by Marcia Barrabee, Peter Darrow, Janet Klaver, Edward Pierce, Melvin Pierce, and Jerry Walden, among others.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Charities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children--Health and hygiene--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pierce, Edward, 1930-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Health and welfare.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Work.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Clinics.; Children.; Clinics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Health care.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pierce, Edward, 1930-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical Files
  - Activities
    - Educational Materials, 1975 and Undated (Box 1)
    - Family Planning, 1973-1977 and Undated (Box 1)
    - Medicaid Case, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Background Information, 1974 and Undated (Box 1)
  - Board
    - By-laws, 1977 and Undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1970-1985 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes (notes, Marcia Barrabee Papers), 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Roster, Undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, General 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Correspondence with Mel Pierce, 1971-1979 (Box 1)
    - General, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - Petty Cash Ledger, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising
    - General, 1970-1985 (Box 1)
    - Johnson Foundation, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - City of Ann Arbor Revenue Sharing, 1973-1974 and Undated (Box 1)
  - Marcia Barrabee Papers--Correspondence, 1976 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Memoranda, 1974-1977 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Michigan Blue Shield, 1972-1975 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Model Cities Health Center, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970, 1971 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Monthly Reports 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Packard Community Clinic (as an independent organization), 1978-2003 (Box 2)
  - Photographs 1971, 1978 and Undated [c1971 and c1979] (Box 2)
  - Policy, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Procedures, 1971-1979 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Publicity
    - Brochures, 1973 and 1978 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1970-1985 and Undated (Box 2)
    - Newsletters, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 2)